<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ecommerce | Akber Choudhry]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.akber.com/blog/categories/ecommerce/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.akber.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-24T03:15:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.akber.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Akber Choudhry]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Linking Dialog and Web Activities in WebSphere Commerce Marketing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.akber.com/linking-dialog-and-web-activities-in-websphere-commerce-marketing"/>
    <updated>2010-10-15T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.akber.com/linking-dialog-and-web-activities-in-websphere-commerce-marketing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>IBM WebSphere Commerce 7.0 comes with a substantial set of marketing activities, namely web activities, e-mail activities and dialog activities.  These are all part of a feature known as &lsquo;Precision Marketing&rsquo; which works roughly as follows:</p>

<p>An active customer action or a background processing action causes a &lsquo;trigger&rsquo; to fire.  If this triggering can be scoped to a &lsquo;target&rsquo; (qualification), then an &lsquo;action&rsquo; occurs. </p>

<p>Activity types: Web and e-mail activities push content along, while dialog activities respond to specific shopper request behaviour.</p>

<p><strong>Poor Man&rsquo;s Recommendation Engine:</strong> Now, a recommendation engine pushes content and products based on past shopper behaviour, whether specific to that shopper, or general past shopper behaviour.</p>

<p>If a dialog activity&rsquo;s end action is to persist captured user behaviour, then triggers and targets based on the persisted behaviour can then be used in a web activity to display specific content.</p>

<p>Thus, combining the two with some custom enhancements that put together some logic and data storage and you may have a specialised recommendation engine for your specific business needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
